so to get started let's take a look at
the template that we're using to render
that home page
and we can see exactly what data we
actually need to display there
and then when we modify this query we'll
make sure that we're only pulling back
that data
for the list and for its to-do's
okay and this is the template that we're
using to display that page
and we can see here that we're accessing
the id for the list
and its name and we're also passing the
list to this list class method
and we're passing the list also to these
other two methods here
to do's remaining count and to use count
so let's go see what those methods are
doing so let's take a look at the
implementation of those methods
and we can decide where to go from there
and here inside today.rb inside the
helpers block
we can find the definition of these
methods
so to use count is actually just
checking the size of the to-do's array
that is
inside the list and today's remaining
count is just counting how many of those
elements inside the titus array have a
value of completed
that is false now it's also worth
knowing that this to-do's remaining
account
method is actually used up here inside
list complete
and so is to-do's count itself
and then of course the question is where
is list complete used
now depending on what ide you use you
may have some nice searching
functionality
a lot of the time for this i will just
go to the console where i'm working on
the project and just use gitgrep
and then type in the code that i'm
looking for in the project
so in this case i want to see where to
do's count is used
if i have the dash n here to get correct
it's going to show me
the line number that's pretty useful so
okay so for to do that rb we're looking
at line 20
and 27. and so yeah that's this line
here
and then down here okay so that's good
so today's count is only used in those
two places
let's check out to do's remaining count
and it looks like it's about the same
situation so that method is used in 2.rb
in one place inside list complete and
then just inside the lists.erb view
template
and while we're checking let's find out
where exactly list complete is being
used
and that's showing up in two other
places inside to do.rb
on line 24 and on line 36.
so here's the first in this case we're
adding the class complete
and this is being used on the page where
we show the list
and it's to-do's and in that case if the
list is complete we cross a few things
out and there's some stylistic changes
it's also being used down here where
we're sorting the lists on the main page
and this is so that lists that are not
yet complete show up above those that
are
so there are a good number of things
that are going to have to change about
the application
if we change the way that the to-do
information is being retrieved from the
database
so let's focus on the main lists page
first get that to work
and then we'll have to come through and
figure out what to do about these other
pieces of the code
that are going to be affected
so if we go back to database persistence
let me go down to the all lists method
here is the query that we're going to
need to change in order to fetch all the
data for this front page
so let's go to the database and use the
postgres console to figure out what
select statement to use
and then we can come back and replace
the query that we're currently using in
that file
with the new one that we've identified
okay so here we are in the postgres
console let's take a look at all the
values in the lists table
okay there they are and then we'll do
the same thing for to do's
okay great so that's the data we're
working with now this is actually the
query that the code is currently using
in that first select statement where
we're just getting all of the lists
so we're going to need to extend this to
also pull in some information about the
to-do's
now if we think about what data we need
about the to use for that page
we actually don't need anything except
the count of how many there are
we just need to render these two numbers
right here and to me that sounds like a
good match for
joining the list table to the to-do's
table grouping by the list id
and then we can use a few count
expressions to create these two values
that we need
for the numbers of different kinds of
to-do's
so we'll start with the same query that
we're currently using so let's start
from lists
and we'll add this to join clause so
we'll say
join to do's
on to do's dot list
id equals lists dot id
okay and so we can see the progress that
we're making here
now what we need to do first of all is
we need to control which columns are
getting back
now in this case we're pulling back all
of the columns both for the lists and
the to-do's table
and we don't really want that
so we'll go back to the beginning of the
query here let's say list stat
asterisk so that'll give us just the
columns for the list table
and then here's where we can add our
accounts so that we can count the number
of to-do so for example we could say
count to do's that id
okay and then this error of course is
because i forgot to add the group
clause to this sql query and it's saying
that you basically can't use
a count expression in the select list
unless you also
have a group being used
so we'll add that here group by
list set id okay
and there's the results so we have now
just the data for the list
and we have the count for how many total
to-do's there are on that list
now it's becoming difficult to edit this
query in the command line
and so here i'll show you a trick that
you can use there's a command called
slash e in the postgresql console
what that's going to do is open up your
default editor
and paste into that editor the last
command that you had put into the
console so for example if i say slash e
here
now my default editor is vim so it's
going to open up vim
and from here i can edit that last query
that i entered into the console
but i can use all the common features of
my editor that i'm familiar with
and this is nice if you're working on
complicated queries or queries with a
lot of parts
because since sql is not white space
sensitive you can break the query up
into multiple lines you can do whatever
you need to so you can actually
see it and edit it more easily and then
what the way this works is you just need
to
save the changes to this file which is
just a temporary file that's been
created for you
and quit the editor and then the
postgres console will take
the value that you've saved to that file
and execute it as if you had typed it at
the prompt
so for instance here i'm going to
do a little bit of editing just to make
this easier to deal with
let's make sure to use a left join so we
get
all of the lists even if they don't have
any to-do's and i'll show you here just
by writing this out and quitting
the console then executes that same
query as if i just typed it directly in
so here's where we are right now we're
selecting the values for the list
we're counting the number of to-do's it
would probably be nice to change the
name of this
column count isn't very specific so
let's call this
to do's count
okay so that's to use count now the
other value that we need
is this first number so we have the
second one which is the total number of
threes
we need this which is the number of
to-do's that have not yet been completed
so let's take a look again at the
valleys in that table and see how we
might
how we might count the number of to do's
that are not yet completed
now the count function in sql returns a
number
that is the total count of how many
values
that are in that column that are not
null
so any other value other than null so
both true and false
are going to be counted and so the
simplest thing that i can think of here
is not going to work so i could say
select count to do's dot completed
and see the count there is going to be
and there are 10 to-do's in the to-do's
table
so that's not going to work we need a
count that's going to only return the
count
of how many are not completed
and this is a case where all the
different functions that are provided by
postgres and the sql standard can really
come in handy
so we really need to do if we're going
to continue to use count is figure out a
way to turn some of the values in this
completed column into nulls
and basically what we want since we want
to count the twos that are not yet
completed
we want to turn any value here that's
true into a null
now fortunately there is just such a
function in sql
and it's called null if
and so what i can do is instead of just
counting
the values of to use that completed i
can say count and then
null if
so just completed is true
so what that will do is null if is going
to return
null if the value in that column is true
otherwise it's just going to return
whatever the actual value is
so that means that the values in the
completed column instead of being true
and false
are going to get null and false and then
because we're passing those into account
count's going to count all the columns
that are not null so it's going to just
ignore
anything that was originally true and in
this way we can count and find that we
have
eight to-do's that need to be completed
so if we take this idea back into our
other sql query
here what we'll do is we'll take this
expression
and we'll add it to the select list here
and then that should provide us with
another column
that will contain the number of to do's
that need to be completed
for each of the lists
and we'll call this column to do's
remaining
okay and so let's take a look at this
data and let's hop back over to the
browser and see if it looks right
so for example aaron's is going to have
four total to do's and three are
remaining
errands has four to do's and three
groceries has two remaining of three
total
here we've got groceries three total and
two remaining
so this looks right so then
this is the query that we need to take
back and add to
our ruby application
and so we need to delete that and then
we need to replace it with the new
query
now here i'm using the here doc syntax
because this is a multiple line
string in ruby and that's a pretty nice
way to do it
so once we execute this statement we
should have all the data that we
actually
need to render that home page the
problem is that we still have this map
loop here
where we're performing additional
queries and we no longer need to fetch
all the to do's
so we'll remove that line we need the id
and the name so we'll leave that alone
and now here let's just change these
values
so instead of to do's we're going to
have to use count
that'll be equal to tuple to do's
count and now remember that's going to
come back to us as a string
so let's just call 2i on that value so
we convert it into
a fixednum object now we're running out
of room here so i might change the way
that this is formatted
and i might actually consolidate this
into this expression
since we're no longer using that list id
value anywhere else
and then we need another value here
let's just say to do's remaining
and we'll do the same thing here
and so now let's come back to the page
where we're rendering this data
and we'll need to update the places to
use this to use count and to use
remaining
instead of those helper methods that we
looked at earlier
so this is the line in question and
right now we're printing out to use
remaining count for list
and then to use count so instead we'll
change this to be
list to do's
remaining and actually we can go back
and change all that to say
to be remaining count everywhere just so
that it's a little more consistent
and then likewise here we'll change this
to be a list
to do's count
save that let's go back to that other
file real quick
i like the consistency of adding count
to the end of these values because they
are
counts
and that way there's some parity between
these two values both in the hash and
in the data that we're pulling out of
the query now don't forget if you change
the value here that you're referencing
from one of these tuples that's returned
we'll need to also rename it up here in
the query where we're actually
creating that value so i'll add count to
the end of that
alias there okay now if i hop back over
here to the browser
i need to of course make sure that the
application is running
and so we have an error so let's figure
out where this is happening
and it looks like the errors in to do's
count
let's figure out where that is actually
occurring
it looks like it's probably going to be
in list class
let's go to to-do.rb
and find the list class and here we're
saying complete if list complete
list and of course now this list
complete method is the one that we saw
earlier
and it's calling into those other two
methods and those are expecting the
to-do's array to be there
all the time so let's change the
implementation of this method
now i'm going to copy it and comment out
the original just so we have it as a
reference
now here we're saying to use count list
is greater than zero
so we can actually just rewrite this
using our new values that we're pulling
out
for that list so to use count
and to do's remaining count this is the
same thing so we can say list
okay so now we're using the new values
that we're returning from the list
from our new query instead of using
these other helper methods
and it looks like we're correctly
displaying all the data for all of these
lists
now something you might have noticed is
that the order of the lists
on this page has changed even though the
values that we're displaying for each
one
have remained consistent the real cause
for this is that
when we're executing that query to pull
back this data we aren't specifying an
order clause
and so it's easy to forget to do that
because a lot of the time
databases are going to return rows to
you basically in the order that they
were created
just because of how they are implemented
internally
but it's best to never depend upon that
behavior because
just as we've seen here as soon as you
change the query a little bit
the results may come back to you in a
different order and so the lesson to
take away from this
is that if you need data to be displayed
in a certain order on your page
make sure that you're using an order
clause to make that order explicit
even if the query is simple and it seems
like it's unnecessary
so we can change that pretty easily here
let's add an order by
and let's order by
let's just order by the list name for
now
now it's possible that maybe in your
application you would actually want to
order them based on
how many total to-do's there are or how
many are remaining but the most
important thing for us is that now the
order is consistent
and something that you can expect
so just as a review for what we've done
here
we've replaced a relatively simple query
with a much more uncomplicated one that
uses a join
and uses a few counts to get all the
data that we need to display a page in a
single query
now if we hop over to the console here
i'll reload this page
the difference is pretty obvious before
we made this change
we were executing many queries on the
database just to display a single page
we had one for lists and then for each
list we were executing an extra query
to get all the to-do's and you can
imagine in a bigger application
maybe we need some information for this
to do and so we'd have to do another
query on top of that for each to do
and you can see how those n plus one
problems can really explode
as the data model that's used by our
application increases in complexity
now what we were able to do in this case
is replace those multiple queries with a
single query
and while it's more complicated this is
going to be a lot more efficient
especially as the size of data
that's managed by the application grows
the other thing to notice about this is
that we're not pulling back
all the data for all the to do's before
because we were saying select asterisk
from to do's we were pulling back their
name
whether they were completed in addition
to their id and the list id
even though we didn't really need that
because we already knew what list we
were getting the to-dos from
based on the query so in this case we're
actually only pulling back
counts of the to-do's and none of the
data for
any of the additional to-do's since we
aren't displaying it on the screen
so this is going to be more efficient
for two reasons one is that there's less
data that has to be sent over the
network from
the database to the application now for
a small query like this on this data set
we aren't going to notice any kind of
difference but for a large data set
or a table that has a lot of columns
something like that can actually make a
difference
the second thing is that all that data
is coming back into our ruby process
and then it has to be managed and
converted into ruby objects so
we're preventing a lot of other work
from happening behind the scenes for
data that we're never going to use
now one thing i want to stress about
this is that this is the kind of
optimization that you should only do
when you've determined that it's
necessary
it's best to write an application with
more general purpose queries
that are going to be less specific and
maybe are not quite as
efficient as they could possibly be but
because they're
more generalized that makes developing
the application further much simpler
however in the future as the application
has continued to develop
you may be able to find places where the
performance of specific pages
seems like it's not quite good enough or
in a case like this you find an n plus
one query
and you have a pretty good idea that
that's eventually going to be a problem
and so those are the times where it
makes sense to go through and change the
code to handle
special case queries like this that are
extracting exactly the data that you
need
from the database in order to perform
the functionality required by the
application